<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands remedy of a deadly malady: the vvise-womans saving the city Abel, by delivering the head of Sheba, who was a traitor to the common-wealth of Israel. Which serveth as a pattern, whereby the City of London may be saved, by the wise endeavours of the citizens thereof, like this wise-womans, (which are upon divine record both for our learning and imitation) even by delivering up to law &amp; justice, the traitors to the common-wealth of England. ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E397_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201676</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862176</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114327</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114327)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E397[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands remedy of a deadly malady: the vvise-womans saving the city Abel, by delivering the head of Sheba, who was a traitor to the common-wealth of Israel. Which serveth as a pattern, whereby the City of London may be saved, by the wise endeavours of the citizens thereof, like this wise-womans, (which are upon divine record both for our learning and imitation) even by delivering up to law &amp; justice, the traitors to the common-wealth of England. ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Englands Remedy of a deadly Malady:</hi> The VViſe-womans SAVING THE CITY ABEL, <hi>BY</hi> Delivering the head of SHEBA, who was a Traitor to the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Which ſerveth as a pattern, whereby the City of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don may be ſaved, by the wiſe endeavours of the Citizens therof, like this Wiſe-womans, (which are upon divine record both for our learning and imitation) even by delivering up to Law &amp; juſtice, the Traitors to the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi> Otherwiſe, if they (under the colour of defending themſelves, Parliament, or City) do any longer ſhelter ſuch wicked men (as vipers in their boſomes) or take up armes againſt our renowned Army, or any having their commiſſion for ſuch a juſt, reaſonable, and lawfull demand, will they not manifeſt to the world, that they themſelves are not onely Traitors to the Common-wealth, both in partaking with the wicked, and condemning the juſt, but are guilty of whatſoever bloudſhed, ruine or deſolation, may poſſibly come upon them and their poſterity? And the malady conſiſteth in the Parliaments injuſtice of all ſorts; ſelf-intereſts, and grinding the faces of the poore; ſuch as their illegall ſentences, unjuſt impriſonments, burning by the common Hang-man, the juſt Petitions of all the free Commons Liberties, detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hire of the labourers, not duly regarding widdowes, fatherleſſe, nor maimed Souldiers: variable Votes, forced Covenants, and time-ſerving Ordinances, even to juſtifie the wicked, and condemn the juſt; and ſo to make all free-borne Engliſh People the worſt of ſlaves, after they are brought low by all ſorts of oppreſſions and deluſions, under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall notions, and have both done all their beſt endeavours, and payed all beyond their powers.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:2"/>
            <head>THE WISE-WOMANS ſaving the City <hi>Abel,</hi> by delivering the head of SHEBA,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> who was a Traytor to the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Which ſerveth as a patterne, whereby the city of <hi>London</hi> may be ſaved, by the wiſe endeavours of the Citizens thereof, like this Wiſe-womans, (who is upon divine record, both for our learning and imitation) even by delivering up to Law and Juſtice, the Traitors to the Common-wealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Otherwiſe if they (under the colour of defending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Parliament or City) do any longer ſhelter ſuch wicked men, (as vipers in their boſomes) or take up armes againſt our renowned Army, or any others, having their Commiſſion, for ſuch a juſt, reaſonable, and lawfull demand, will they not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the whole world, that they themſelves are not onely Traitors alſo to the Common-wealth, both in partaking with the wicked, and condemning the juſt, but are guilty of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever blood-ſhed, ruine, or deſolation, may poſſibly come upon them and their poſterity?</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jonah 1.15. Prov. 28.28. &amp; 14.34. &amp; 11.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So they tooke up Jonah, and caſt him into the ſea, and the ſea ceaſed from her raging.</p>
                  <p>When the wicked riſe, men hide themſelves, but when they periſh, the righteous increaſe.</p>
                  <p>Juſtice exalteth a nation, but ſin is a ſhame to any people.</p>
                  <p>In the proſperity of the righteous the city rejoyceth, and when the wicked pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, there is joy.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SO ſoon as the Kingdome of Iſrael was delivered from <hi>Abſolons</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there aroſe another Rebell againſt King <hi>David,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Sheba,</hi> who tooke occaſion from the emulation and hot contention, which was between the ten Tribes,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> concerning the bringing back of the King to Jeruſalem, even to blow the bellowes, and kindle the fire of diviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb facs="tcp:114327:3"/>them, whiles the coles were hot, and to proclaime with ſound of Trumpet in the name of all the ten Tribes, We have no part in <hi>David</hi> neither have we inheritance in the Sonne of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> to your Tents O Iſrael</p>
            <p>So that by the inſtigation of this one wicked man, there was a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made between many thouſands of Brethren and Friends, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended all of one ſtock, even a revolt of the ten Tribes, and ſo a rent of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdome.</p>
            <p>As this <hi>Sheba</hi> being here deſcribed by his brethren and kindred to be the ſon of <hi>Bichri</hi> and of <hi>Benjamins</hi> Tribe, as King <hi>Saul</hi> was, ſo was he of <hi>Saul</hi> ſpightfull diſpoſition, ſtill retaining the bitter taſte of the old caske of <hi>Sauls</hi> Court, which is alſo noted of <hi>Shimei,</hi> by his reviling of <hi>David,</hi> when he was driven away by <hi>Abſolon;</hi> both which old Courtiers, had not yet layed aſide their old grudge againſt <hi>David</hi> and the State of his Kingdome</p>
            <p>The vigilancy and activity of this treacherous <hi>Sheba</hi> is thus noted, that when he ſeeth <hi>David</hi> at the weakeſt, then he taketh moſt advantage in the purſuance of his deſigne to be ſtrongeſt, draweth the ten Tribes into his faction, and betaketh himſelfe to <hi>Abel</hi> a ſtrong and walled City, whereof <hi>Joab</hi> (the chiefe Captain of <hi>Davids</hi> hoſt) having intelligence, he preſently layeth ſiege to the City, deſtroyeth and caſteth downe the walls thereof being (as it ſeems) provoked thereunto by the Citizens, ſtanding out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſiege in a wrong cauſe, even in defence of the Ttraytor <hi>Sheba</hi> under colour of defending their City.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Joab</hi> (it appeares) had no quarrell at all to the City, it being a branch of the King his Maſters Kingdome, but onely as it was an obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to hinder his purſuit againſt one Rebell and his faction in the City who had thus highly offended the King; ſo that there is a diſtinction here to be made between the Citie it ſelfe, and the traiterous faction of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators which were ſheltered therein, whereof this <hi>Sheba</hi> was the head.</p>
            <p>Upon this fierce aſſault by <hi>Joab,</hi> thus provoked in his zeale for the weale of the Kingdome, and for avoiding of further ſtrife and diviſion, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God (in his tender compaſſion of the City) to move a woman of the City, to cry from the wal to <hi>Joabs</hi> Souldiers, that <hi>Joab</hi> would come near and ſpeake with her; by this her deſiring a parle, and the event thereof, ſhe is called (as ſhe truly deſerveth) a wiſe woman, becauſe ſhe taketh the wiſeſt and beſt courſe to preſerve the City, as doth appeare alſo by the effect.</p>
            <p>Whereas if ſhe had not by her wiſdome broken off both the folly of the Citizens, and the furie of the Adverſaries, it might have poſſibly been turned to aſhes, and by that meanes many thouſands therein who knew not the right hand from the left, (as well as others of greater age) might
<pb facs="tcp:114327:3"/>have been brought to great miſerie, if not ſpeedy deſtruction: So that to ſtand out in defence and maintenance of Traytors and Enemies to the common weale, under the ſpecious pretence of defending a City, and not render them up to juſtice, upon juſt and lawfull demand, is enough to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke both God and man to puniſh the whole City, for ſo many wicked and traiterous <hi>Sheba's</hi> as be ſheltered therein.</p>
            <p>We read of this very Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> formerly,<note place="margin">Judg. 19.20, 21. Chap.</note> that for their unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly maintaining and not juſtly puniſhing that horrid fact of thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> amongſt them, who abuſed the Levites Concubine to death, all the other Tribes of Irael roſe up in armes as one man, and revenged it upon them to their deſtruction, though they were their brethren, and that for their wicked obſtinacy in that hainous ſin, without any repentance or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow: ſo that of five and twenty thouſand mighty and valourous men, onely ſix hundred eſcaped to tell newes.</p>
            <p>And if for want and refuſall of doing juſtice in ſuch a particular caſe, the ten Tribes roſe up and deſtroyed almoſt a whole Tribe, and that by the Commandement of God himſelf, ſeeing thoſe who were guiltleſs, took part with the guilty, and ſo the whole lump leavened alike: then how is a whole Kingdome engaged to take revenge of any part thereof, which doth labour and maintaine notorious Traytors and malicious Enemies to the Common-wealth, when juſtice is demanded of them? For as God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all wickedneſſe, injuſtice, tyranny and oppreſſion, amongſt particular or private men, ſo how much more doth he hate treaſon and treachery, againſt a whole Nation or Common-wealth?</p>
            <p>But howſoever, whether they either forbeare or doe their endeavour, though hand joyne in hand, the wicked ſhall not be unpuniſhed: ſuch grievous deſignes doe never go ſcot-free, but are revenged of God or his inſtruments, without ſpeedy repentance to prevent ſuch deſerved judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and no Nation in the world can ſhew more famous examples in this kind then England, it being ſo often attempted to be betrayed both by ſtrangers and others, but ſtill preſerved of God (to his everlaſting praiſe.) Inſomuch that a famous man ſaid of England, <hi>Regnum Angliae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polydor. Virgil.</note>
               <hi>Regnum Dei,</hi> the Kingdome of England is Gods Kingdome, for none ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth any true of reall care of preſerving it, but God only.</p>
            <p>One word by the way, the Author of this Dictaum living in England, did well obſerve what a careleſſe, wicked, and ſelfe-betraying State it hath ever been, conſiſting of a mixt people gathered out of ſeverall Nations, and therefore he attributed to God alone, the many and miraculous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances of this ſinfull Nation, as we have far greater cauſe now then he had then, to acknowledge in all theſe ſeven yeares Occurrences, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:114327:4"/>by the miſcarriage of that bloody Petition, which ſhould have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by thrice forty thouſand armed men, for which the wars began; the deliverance at Edge-hill, Newbery, &amp; Brainford, when we ſhould have been abſolutely betrayed, had not God onely been on our ſide, and ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the Lord of hoſts, and God of battells, in ſo mightily reſcuing and delivering us out of the jawes and clawes of all our mighty and ſtrong enemies, who were ready and bent at all thoſe occaſions to devoure and ſwallow us up from being a people any more.</p>
            <p>But to adhere to our intended purpoſe: this wiſe-woman taketh cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſpeaketh to <hi>Ioab:</hi> Was not this a wonder, that there was never a wiſe man in this City? But God who oftentimes ſaveth both by weake inſtruments, and deſpiſed meanes, was pleaſed to make this woman the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of thus uſing the meanes in ſaving a beſieged city in Iſrael, from all the power and forces of a great King; even as he made that poor wiſe man ſpoken of by <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.</note> the inſtrument of delivering another City, who therefore declared, that <hi>wiſdome was better then weapons of warre, and yet no man regarded</hi> (much leſſe rewarded) <hi>that poore wiſe man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Abigail</hi> the wife of <hi>Nabal</hi> was a happy inſtrument to pacifie the fury of King <hi>David</hi> and all his followers againſt her husband for his churl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.</note> ſo was this woman to aſswage the fury of <hi>Ioab</hi> the chief Captain of all his forces here againſt this city: and it pleaſed God ſo to bleſse the means which thoſe two women uſed, that both the King and <hi>Ioab</hi> heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened to their good counſell, and were contented to depart in peace, without offering injury or violence to any: So that it is good not to ſleight the wholſome advice of an inferiour, more then an equall, or a ſuperiour. If <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian had deſpiſed the good counſell of his own wiſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and not waſhed himſelfe in Jordan,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.19</note> according to the direction of the Prophet, rather then in the rivers of Damaſcus, he might have returned home, and died in his leproſie; yea and beſides, he had not been ſo well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and perſwaded in his faith againſt his former ignorance and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which he confeſsed upon his cleanſing, and thankfull returning to the Prophet, who cured him. If King <hi>Ahab</hi> had not hated <hi>Micaiah,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged his wiſe and good counſell,<note place="margin">1 King. 22.</note> againſt his going up to Ramoth-Gile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad, he had not loſt his life and kingdome: but he following the wicked advice of falſe Prophets, who ſtirred him up to make a new warre, was one cauſe both of his owne, and his poſterities ruine.</p>
            <p>As falſe Prophets are known by many other bitter fruits, ſo chiefly by theſe two ſpeciall marks. Firſt, they are alwayes eager and thirſty after blood, both like their father the Devill that murderer from the beginning, and that Whore mentioned in the <hi>Revelation.</hi> And next, they are no wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:114327:4"/>ſo hot for juſt peace, as for unjuſt warre. Was not Jeruſalems deſtruction the more deſerved, becauſe they hearkened to falſe Prophets, that ſpake lies in the name of the Lord, and deſpiſed the true Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> who ſpake as the Lord immediately directed him. And did not that zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> himſelfe, after all his matchleſſe reformation, receive a mortall wound for going out inconſiderately to battell againſt <hi>Pharoah Neho</hi> king of Egypt (as is likely) without advice either of God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 34, 35.</note> or <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> the Prophet? yea and diſtruſting that <hi>Pharoah</hi> came not forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but his enemies the Aſſyrians: and though his intention was juſt and good, even to defend his own Land, yet for this his treſpaſſe of teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and raſhneſſe, he was puniſhed with temporall death, but being ſo worthy a King, there was more mourning and greater lamentation for him, then any King that ever was in the world: Oh for ſuch a good King as <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and ſuch a grave Parliament as the Elders of <hi>Judah</hi> and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem were in his daies! then we ſhould have a bleſſed and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reformation not only in word and ſhew, but in deed and ſubſtance, to ſome purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, this woman is not like too many now adaies, who claime unjuſt titles, for ſhe well deſerveth her title to be called wiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is ſo indeed, in that ſhe thus loveth a juſt peace, and hateth an unjuſt warre, which is the main end and ſcope of her parle with <hi>Joab;</hi> and is ſhe is very excellent in the pacifying of <hi>Joabs</hi> furie by forcible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo is ſhe no leſſe active and reſolute in perſwading the people of the City by ſound reaſons, to yeeld to her juſt deſires, both for their own ſafety and that which is their bound duty, even to deliver the head of <hi>Sheba</hi> that Traytor, who ſo troubled the Common-wealth of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>And therefore as God bleſſed her as a peace-maker, in prevailing with <hi>Joab,</hi> ſo alſo with the people, (for they finding her reaſons to be juſt and right, ordered to cut off the head of <hi>Sheba,</hi> and to caſt it over the walls to <hi>Joab,</hi> which accordingly was done) ſo <hi>Joab</hi> blew the Trumpet, retired from the City, and every man to his Tent: Thus by the meanes of thoſe unto whom God giveth wiſdome to order things aright, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ſoever they be in the eyes of the world, both good duties may be timely performed, evill conſequences wiſely prevented, yea and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy judgements removed, as we ſee alſo by the happy iſſue of <hi>Phineas</hi> his zeal in the execution of <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Coſbi,</hi> even in the very act of their hainous ſin of Adultery. And without the execution of juſtice, here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by <hi>Joab,</hi> there is no peace with <hi>Joab,</hi> yea no peace with God; for if he (the Lord of Hoſts) be offended and no meanes uſed nor followed whereby his anger may be aſſwaged, as he is a juſt God, and the true owner
<pb facs="tcp:114327:5"/>of vengeance, he muſt needs be revenged, and hath all the creatures at his call, alwaies to execute his Will, as by one Angell hee ſmote a hundred fourſcore and five thouſand of <hi>Senacheribs</hi> Army in one night; howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wicked men (who he oftentimes catcheth in the very ſame ſnares which they lay for others) thinketh that he hath neither number enough of inſtruments, nor magazine great enough of judgements to catch them in the height and purſuit of their ſins.</p>
            <p>What a vaine queſtion was that of <hi>Joram</hi> to <hi>Jehu?</hi> Is it peace <hi>Jehu?</hi> What peace anſwered he, ſo long as the whoredomes of thy mother <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabel,</hi> and her witchcrafts are ſo many? God would have juſtice done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bloody houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and upon <hi>Ieſabel</hi> for <hi>Naboths</hi> blood, what peace can be then till this be done? So here was a wicked <hi>Sheba,</hi> a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to the State, who with his ſtrong faction intended the overthrow of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdome, which was a type of Chriſts Kingdome, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to nullifie the priviledges and liberties of the free-born people, for his owne coverous and ambitious ends.</p>
            <p>This wiſe woman likewiſe profeſſeth her ſelfe to <hi>Ioab,</hi> to be one of them that are peaceable and faithfull in Iſrael, and this ſhe doth not for her own private reſpects only, but much more for the common-weale of <hi>Abel</hi> her City: To bee peaceable is very commendable, but eſpecially in one who alſo is faithfull; for, peacableneſſe hath moſt reſpect to man, but faithfulneſſe both to God and man; to God, in holding forth his truth, and to man, in giving good example by holy converſation, that men ſeeing the good workes of faith (which are wrought by love) may glorifie God, and (through his grace) become of the ſame profeſſion: And faithfulneſſe alſo to man doth conſiſt in the diſcharge of all duties, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of that truſt which thoſe who have undoubted power, do commit to the charge of thoſe whom they chuſe: and the other do not onely undertake, but faithfully vow and promiſe to performe with all their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the publike good: and herein, if they be either remiſſe, corrupt, or falſe, doe they not falſifie their faith, and betray that great truſt, by bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their affections, and imploying all their ſtudies for their own private ends: ſo that by this meanes they transforme themſelves from being any more Truſtees, but become a faction of Traitors to the people who depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, not to advance themſelves as maſters, but the Common-wealth whereof they are ſervants, excepting ſo farre as their owne ſhare is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p>This faithfulneſſe both to God and man finds ſo little favour and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment now adayes, that it is accounted rather a vice then a vertue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept onely among ſuch as be alſo faithfull and well-principled: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:114327:5"/>though they who hate faithfulneſſe and faithfull men doe in word and ſhew pretend peace, yet in deed and ſubſtance they hunt after warre, like to thoſe deceitfull Prophets that bite with their teeth and cry peace, but he that putteth not into thir mouthes, they prepare war againſt him, even as now their brethren thoſe popiſh Prieſts and Engliſh tythe-mongers, doe ſtill in theſe ſad daies of Englands miſery.</p>
            <p>And as this wiſe woman is peaceable, ſo ſhe is faithfull, and ſo peaceable and ſo faithfull, that the peace ſhe ſeeketh is ſo juſt, and the faith ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteth is ſo true, that ſhe permitteth neither of them to putrifie by reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home with her ſelfe, but ſo imployeth them in the works of love, that they extend themſelves and run like cleare rivers abroad unto others, and that not to a few friends, neighbours, nor familiars, but to the whole City where ſhe liveth.</p>
            <p>Another point of her wiſdome may be obſerved, firſt, in the wiſe and ſure foundation of her arguments from Gods Word, and next by the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtating thereof by way of interrogatories or queſtions, as the moſt choice and pregnant wayes to daunt the fury either of friends or adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and that even by giving them ſome hint of their own fault in their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement purſuance of revenge, otherwiſe (as it ſeemeth) then by due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, eſpecially when there is no other forcible nor probable means of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, as appeareth by the ſtory.</p>
            <p>She chargeth <hi>Ioab</hi> (as it ſeems) with a breach of Gods Law, where it is forbidden (<hi>Deut.</hi> 20.10, 11.) to fight againſt a City untill peace be offered unto it, which (belike) he had not done, and therefore apprehending his own ignorance or negligence, was touched by the truth, ſenſe, and force of her words; as alſo ſhe thus pleadeth; as if ſhe ſhould ſay, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever others may out of their unadviſedneſſe make ſome reſiſtance to <hi>Ioab</hi> and his Army, contrary to her mind and will, yet ſhe (not being able to amend nor hinder them) for her own part, is one of them that are peaceable and faithfull in the City, yea and a mother in Iſrael: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why would hee preſume or offer to deſtroy the inheritance of the Lord?</p>
            <p>The ſad apprehenſion of which words, made ſuch a deep impreſſion in <hi>Ioabs</hi> heart, that he very ſoberly and diſcreetly cleared himſelfe, by the reality and integrity of his intentions, ſaying, God forbid; <hi>God forbid it me, that I ſhould devoure or deſtroy it:</hi> the matter is not ſo, but a man of Mount Ephraim (<hi>Sheba</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bichri</hi> by name) hath lift up his hand againſt the King, even againſt <hi>David,</hi> deliver us him onely, and I will depart from the City: and the woman ſaid, Behold his head ſhall be thrown to thee over the wall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:6"/>
            <p>Then the woman went unto all the people with her wiſdome, and they cut off the head off <hi>Sheba,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Bichri,</hi> and caſt it to <hi>Ioab,</hi> then he blew the Trumpet, and they retired from the Citie, every man to his Tent and <hi>Ioab</hi> returned to Jeruſalem unto the King.</p>
            <p>To prevent an Objection here, in the wiſe womans ſpeech to <hi>Joab,</hi> ſhe ſaith thus, they ſpake in the old time ſaying, they ſhould aske of <hi>Abell,</hi> and ſo have they continued; now whether ſhe meaneth onely the place, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the ſame by the name, that thoſe who beſiege a City (as the City <hi>Abell</hi>) ought firſt to offer peace to that City, as is formerly obſerved, of that <hi>Joab</hi> and his ſouldiers ought to have asked of the City <hi>Abell,</hi> whether or no they would deliver <hi>Sheba,</hi> and to have offered them peace upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverie of him, and not to have broken down the wall without any ſuch queſtion or condition, contrary to the Law of God, common ſenſe and cuſtome, which may be drawne from theſe words of her ſpeech, and ſo have they continued, or that they ſhould aske concerning the perſon <hi>Abel,</hi> calling to mind his innocent blood, alluding to the people in the City, who had not procured ſuch an aſſault, by any miſdemeanour proceeding from themſelves, either of which ſenſes or interpretations, may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent enough to the ſcope of what ſhe intended, in her diſpute or ſpeech to <hi>Ioab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the reaſon why <hi>Ioab</hi> was ſo eaſily pacified from all his fury, and getting juſtice onely againſt one Traytor, though there were a number of others in the City, he himſelfe declareth in the Hiſtorie, that the intent of his coming was to have juſtice onely againſt one man, and the cauſe was formerly ſhewed, even that he was the ring-leader to all the reſt in rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; according to the old true proverb, which a Member of the Parliament for once repeating in the Houſe (where oftentimes truth hath no place nor admittance) <hi>pereat unus potius quàm unitas,</hi> it is better that one (or a few) periſh, then a multitude, Corporation City, or Nation, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the barre and committed to priſon, where he continued for a whole yeare at leaſt.</p>
            <p>Now all that is to be inferred from what is here ſpoken, doth briefly tend to this effect, there are many opinions concerning the intentions of our renowned Army, eſpecially for their advancing to this City: Why? whats the matter? Doth it not conſiſt of very rationall men? And doe not you think, but they have many ſtrong reaſons and both weighty and urgent cauſes for what they doe: We not only know by report but feel by experience, that there is not only one <hi>Sheba</hi> among us, but too many ring-leaders of rebellion, incendiaries of ſedition, and raiſers of anew warre, which the Army doe demand and perſue, that they may be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:114327:6"/>up to the law, and tryed according to juſtice, which is the firſt and moſt ſpeciall and effectuall meanes to recover both our Lawes, peace and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; out of which all the free-born people of <hi>England</hi> are like to bee ſtript naked, and ſo are in a moſt dangerous capacitie of ſlaverie and miſerie.</p>
            <p>And if there be ſuch treacherous enemies to the Common-wealth and betrayers of there truſt concerning the recoverie and defence of our Lawes and liberties, detained ſheltered and maintained in and about the Citie of London, as that Rebell <hi>Sheba</hi> was in the Citie <hi>Abell,</hi> is there ſo much as my ſhew or colour of reaſon to the contrary, but that the whole people of the land as one man (if it were poſſible) ſhould ſeek all lawfull and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly redreſſe for juſtice: as in the caſe of the ten Tribes, againſt that of <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> before cited, and of <hi>Achan, Ieſabel</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>Therefore whoſoever or how many ſoever ſhall oppoſe them in ſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and needfull apurſuit, will manifeſt themſelves to be as great Traytors and enemies to the Commons of England as the other, who are thus impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, yea and if it were in the way of revenge, failing of ordinary juſtice, (as this act of <hi>Joabs</hi> purſuing <hi>Sheba</hi> may ſeem to be) it is neither cruelty nor war, but rather a ſeeking of juſtice, and conſequently of peace, in ſo following after it.</p>
            <p>One thing is to be feared, and another to be wiſhed; the firſt is, that the Citizens are not ſo diligent to treat with the Parliament for doing of juſtice, as they are with the Army for yeelding to peace without juſtice: for this woman was as carefull to deale with the Citizens, as ſhe was with <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi> ſo ſoon as ſhe knew his mind: And the next is, that neither Parliament not City permit their Clergie any more to preach war in the City; and peace in the Army, nor that ſuch Incendiaries nor deceivers (as thoſe Prieſts and their followers) be ſuffered any more to intice and poyſon, yea and undermine the weaker ſort of the Army, but be quite returned.</p>
            <p>As this wiſe woman undertaketh, begineth, procedeth, and proſpereth, in this great buſineſſe, as appeareth by <hi>Ioab</hi> and the Citizens both hearing and following her councells, becauſe they all attend to juſtice, ſo by that moſt powerfull, effectuall, and commendable meanes, which ſhe uſeth, it pleaſeth God ſo to order the buſineſſe, that thereby juſtice is duly and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily executed, and ſo all is made quiet, even as when <hi>Ionah</hi> was caſt into the ſea, the powerfull raging thereof was changed into a great calme.</p>
            <p>But in regard the matter is hiſtoricall, and needeth litle illuſtration, or ſcarce any application, it being ſo ſuitable to our preſent condition, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will adde a ſimile for concluſion; this whole Kingdome at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of this Parliament, may be parallelled with <hi>Gedions</hi> Army of two and thirty thouſand, when he went to battel againſt the Midianites, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:114327:7"/>of our greater quantity or number, but rather of our quality and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, this Nation being a mixed people, like <hi>Gideons</hi> Army of good and bad ſouldiers, able and unable, whereof the greateſt part were the open enemies of our peace, and ſo verie unfit to fight for our lives, Lawes or Liberties, at leaſt whileſt they were under that banner.</p>
            <p>But thoſe two and thirty thouſand being fined, and a party ſingled out from amongſt them, extending to ten thouſand, which were not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo timorous, and therefore ſomewhat more likely to carry on the worke in the day of battell: this party is like our mixed Parliamentary multitude, being choſen by all ſorts, or rather ſeveral diſpoſitions of people as appeareth by the fruit and effect proceeding from the cauſe, and as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry living creature doth naturally produce and bring forth others both of the ſame kind and ſimilitude.</p>
            <p>And theſe ten thouſand of <hi>Gideons</hi> Army who were thus fined, being ſtill unfit for the intended buſineſſe notwithſtanding, therefore they were refined to three hundred, which may be accounted thoſe military members of valourous and victorious Souldiers of our Army, by whom as the Lord hath done great works to his endleſſe praiſe, ſo our hope is, that the ſame God will do yet greater works againſt both our open and ſecret enemies, yea and pretended friends, to his owne glorie and all our comforts who truſt in him, either by them or others.</p>
            <p>We bleſſe his divine Majeſtie, that like this wiſe woman he hath made this City ſo wiſe, as to ſend forth ſome of their Aldermen and other anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents to parle with that renowned Army concerning the preſent expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of whoſe wiſdome and fidelity both to the City, Parliament, and Common-wealth, as they have had already very ſufficient, ſo ſhall they have (no doubt) abundant ſatisfaction; yea and will (we hope) crown the ſame with ſuch happy and gratious effects to the joy of all faithfull and true-hearted Engliſh, both of this age, and all ſucceeding ages, as never King nor Parliament together nor apart did the like, ſince England was firſt a plantation, before it began to be a Nation.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:7"/>
            <head>The Maladie, conſiſting in the Parliaments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of all ſorts, ſelfe-intereſtes and grinding the faces of the poore, ſuch as their illegall ſentences, unjuſt impriſonments, burning (by the common-hangman) the juſt Petitions of all the Commons Liberties, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MAy not England now ſay, behold and ſee, all ye that paſſe by, is there any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow? Is not this our our fruitfull land, like to become a barren wilderneſſe, even for the wickedneſſe of the Inhabitants? Is not this fearfull judgment of new wars juſtly deſerved, both for the crying ſins and great abominations which ſo powerfully raign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all eſtates, even from the higheſt to the loweſt? And that not alwaies nor altogether by meanes of profeſſed enemies, but rather as often, and ſometimes much more of pretended friends, yea even of a ſtrong party in our own houſhold of Commons: for that Houſe being (as it were) the ſalt to ſeaſon all the unſavoury practices and proceedings of others, by their aſſembling for that buſineſſe, in the behalf of all the Commons of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, if they themſelves ſhould loſe the ſavour, wherewith ſhall they bee ſalted? Will they in ſuch a caſe be good for any thing, but to be caſt out is corrupt and rotten Members?</p>
            <p>What people or Nation did ever more freely not only adventure, but even ſacrifice their lives, blood, livelihoods and eſtates in the defence and for the maintenance both of the Parliaments owne lives, Priviledges and eſtates (even when they had neither Army nor Guard) ſo long as they ſeemed to ſtand for our Lives, Lawes and Liberties, which they have ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten promiſed, proteſted, declared, vowed and ſworne to recover and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and we ſo long expected, yea and have ſo much deſerved, as well by the right of purchaſe, as of birth and native inheritance.</p>
            <p>Long have we and our Predeceſſors ſighed and groaned under the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burdens of former oppreſſions, by meanes of cruell task-maſters, even for a Parliament of ſix months, (never ſo much as dreaming of ſeven years) and that to have had our juſt Petitions granted, and our unjuſt grievances redreſſed, all wicked Lawes aboliſhed, and good Lawes eſtabliſhed, wee
<pb facs="tcp:114327:8"/>looked for comfort, but behold ſorrow; we have only a charge of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, but ſtill the ſame oppreſſions, though under other notions.</p>
            <p>And did not our owne Houſe of Commons, whom we both chooſed and truſted to defend our Lawes and liberties, at their firſt ſitting ſo aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly encourage us, both by their legall practiſes and faire carriages, that we could not with any conſcience of our duties, or ſenſe of our miſeries, deny to adventure our lives, nor beſtow our eſtates for their help, mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and aſſiſtance? For did not they releaſe the priſoners, bring home the baniſhed, utter many excellent ſpeeches in the defence of our Laws, Liberties, Perſons and eſtates? Did not they aboliſh the Star-Chamber, High Commiſſion, and Councell-Table Monopolies, and Ship-moneyes? Did not they demoliſh many Croſſes, May-poles, and high Altars? And, did they not make many Faſt-dayes, and begin to bring wicked men to condigne puniſhment?</p>
            <p>But ſo ſoon as they by theſe plauſible, powerfull and effectuall meanes, and the Clergies eloquence, had got into their hands the Common-wealths moneyes, plate, and all things elſe, which might either encourage or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a number of ſouldiers to bring home the King with ſome bad Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors from Yorke to the Parliament, they ſo taſted the ſweetneſſe and benefit thereof, that they not onely uſed all forcible and effectuall means to get more and more of the Kingdoms money at their diſpoſe, untill they not onely made themſelves rich, and the Common-wealth poore, but out of their abundance did divide the ſpoile, which cometh by the ruines of the people liberally amongſt themſelves, and ſend upon all conuenient oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions beyond the Seas, ſo that theſe our Truſtees at Weſtminſter, are quite changed and degenerated from their firſt love, and have betrayed that great and publike truſt which all the Commons of England have repoſed in them, which was chiefly to rectifie all kind of Tyranny and Oppreſſion, but therein are ſo ſhort, that they are become the greateſt Tyrants and Oppreſſors themſelves.</p>
            <p>For, do they not only hate and diſcountenance all who have been their beſt and trueſt friends, in their greateſt both wants and other extremities, but preferre to all places of truſt, power and command, both in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Common-wealth, even thoſe who have aſſiſted their and our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies in theſe times, and have been alwayes refractary to all goodneſſe? Do they not ſtill reject (as they have done for a long time) all worthy Petitions for Englands Liberties, and very thankfully accept all that are deſtructive, croſſe or contrary thereunto?</p>
            <p>Do they not onely advance thoſe who ſeek to undermine, ſell and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray both us, themſelves and poſterities, with all our freedomes, for ſome
<pb facs="tcp:114327:8"/>preferments, baſe or private reſpects, to fulfill their owne luſts, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe impriſon, threaten and revile the other well-affected party, calling them factious and ſeditious enemies to the State, and the like, who do pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for ſuch lawfull priviledges as is their due to have, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments duty to give, yea and condemne ſome of thoſe honeſt and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able peoples beſt Petitions, which do contain all Englands liberties, to be burned by the common Hang-man?</p>
            <p>And did they not onely moſt unjuſtly and undutifully reject the juſt and humble Petitions of divers worthy Counties lately for the ſame Liberties? Do they not ſtill oppreſſe the poore, and grind their faces, by paying of Exciſe, rather then ſubſide according to Law and reaſon, to lay ſuch burdens for the publike good on the rich, who have lands and abilities to beare and indure them? and yet notwithſtanhing, the publike debts and Souldiers are unpayed, widdowes, fatherleſſe and maimed ſouldiers unprovided, and the publike treaſurie emptied.</p>
            <p>Yea and which doth reach higheſt of all, they are growne to ſuch an impudency both of injuſtice and ingratitude, againſt that worthy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Army who preſerved their lives, and ſecured their eſtates, that when they were addreſſing themſelves to petition their own Generall, concerning very modeſt and reaſonable requeſts, that he might (if he thought expedient) preſent them to the Houſe, they declared highly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that juſt Petition of the Army, and all the Army themſelves, calling them enemies to the State, and the like, if they proceeded any further therein, and endeavoured by all poſſible means either to disband, divide, or delude them, though ſince (upon not prevailing, and the Armies ſtanding) they have recalled that Declaration, without any regard either to juſtice, honour, ſin or ſhame, thinking thereby to have given the Army ſome kinde of ſatisfaction, by ſuch counterfeit repentance, and forced humiliation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as if the Army, who have the ſword to act, and they but the word to vote, would have been deceived by them, as they have cheated the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
            <p>But to be ſhort, becauſe we are all like to be aſſaulted with a ſtronger temptation then ever we were heretofore, and that very ſpeedily, we have great need therefore to caſt our greateſt care and confidence on God, and then we need not care nor feare what man can do, we will be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all either by flatterie or force, if not by both, to go up (as it were) to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>math-Gilead and proſper, even to take up armes againſt our owne beloved brethren and countrey-men, fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone, that moſt terrible Army with Banners, who through God, have done valiantly in ſubduing all our open enemies: but we muſt altogether refuſe, upon
<pb facs="tcp:114327:9"/>whatſoever tearms offered or pretended, leaſt in obeying the luſts and arbitrary wills of wicked, covetous, ambitious and time-ſerving men, who thirſt after blood, thinke to eſcape in the preſſe, and ſtill fiſh in troubled waters, we fight againſt <hi>God,</hi> be traytors to our Countrey, guilty of much innocent blood, abſolve the wicked, condemne the juſt, and ſhew our ſelves (both by evill example and otherwiſe) both unjuſt and unthankfull, even in rendring evill for good, as now the Parliament doth to us.</p>
            <p>For as this Army, when former Armies could not, have been the chiefeſt inſtruments of delivering us from regall oppreſſion, ſo they are the moſt hopefull worldly power to free us from Parliamentary corruption, to ſee the time of each Parliament limited, and how often to be called, juſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie for tender conſciences provided, juſt Lawes made and executed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Lawes aboliſhed, our juſt Petitions received, read and granted, our grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances redreſſed, this Parliament from all corrupt Members purged, all our juſt Liberties recovered, all who are unjuſtly impriſoned, juſtly relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and their illegall ſufferings of all others ſince the Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, legally repaired, the great accounts of the publike Treaſurie required, widdowes, fatherleſſe, maimed ſouldiers, and all other ſorts of poor main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, juſt men advanced to places of truſt, both in Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and unjuſt men depoſed and puniſhed, ſo ſhall it bee well with us, and our poſterity throughout all Generations.</p>
            <p>But if otherwiſe, we yeeld now to wicked mens deſires, for their owne covetous and ambitious ends, and no good to us, when we have done all we can, yea and paſt the bounds of our abilities, we ſhall have no more thanks nor reward, then now we have of the Parliament for all our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable both actions and ſufferings, but be made ſuch kinde of beggars and ſlaves, both in our ſpirituall and temporall conditions, as we ſhall bee a proverbe and a hiſſing to all Nations, even as Gods owne peculiar people the Jewes were, who had many happie opportunities and gracious influences of Gods ſpeciall favours, to have made them the moſt renowned, famous, yea and invincible people that ever were upon the face of the earth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>An Appendix containing divers worthy particulars belonging to the premiſes, which doe moſt conſiſt in Objections and Anſwers.</head>
            <p>IF any doe demand why the Remedie is placed here before the Maladie, it is done becauſe there be too many maladies and too few remedies, and therefore I place here firſt what is rareſt, and laſt which is ofteneſt or
<pb facs="tcp:114327:9"/>moſt frequent, as the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> had his cure and remiſſion ready, to pronounce for <hi>Davids</hi> ſins, before ever he by his wiſe parable, convinced him thereof.</p>
            <p>And whereas ſome may object, that our Army under the command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> have not ſuch power and authority of King nor King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to demand thoſe eleven Members of the Houſe of Commons, to be ſecured and delivered up to juſtice, as <hi>Joab</hi> had of King <hi>David</hi> or his Kingdome, to purſue <hi>Sheba,</hi> or beſiege a City for him? It is anſwered, that the Captaine Generall of our Army, hath as much power and authority at leaſt, to doe what he hath now undertaken, as <hi>Ioab</hi> the Captaine Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of King <hi>Davids</hi> Army had, for what he undertook: for as the one tended to the well and ſafety of that Kingdome, ſo the other tendeth to the well and ſafety of this Kingdome, which is, and alwaies ſhould be, the maine end both of all wars and governments. If either the Citizens of London had offered, or the Army of England had deſired, the heads of theſe eleven Members, as was both offered and accepted concerning <hi>Sheba,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that ſo reaſonable a demand to have their perſons only, to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live ſecured untill they be tried, it might have imported ſeverity in the one, and cruelty in the other; but ſince neither were ſo much as once mentioned, wherein then is the Army unjuſt, unreaſonable, unequitable or any wiſe cruell, as both Parliament-men, who have ſo bad a conſcience that they cannot indure triall, and others would ſuggeſt and ſurmiſe to the rude people, even by their baſe Queries and other aſperſions, which they imploy ſuch as themſelves alſo to divulge?</p>
            <p>If it be objected, that the Citizens of London are not ſo able to ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite or importune the Parliament of England for juſtice in this kind for the Army, as the wiſe woman and Citizens of <hi>Abel,</hi> were to procure ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of ſuch forces belonging to the ten Tribes, as did accompany <hi>Sheba</hi> to that City in this his rebellion? It is anſwered, that the Citizens of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don are more able, not only to ſolicite, but even to prevail with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for thoſe eleven men for divers reſpects, which may be eaſilier under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, then the Citizens of <hi>Abel</hi> were with the ten Tribes concerning <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> yea and the ten Tribes of Iſrael were as great (I ſuppoſe) for that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to deale with, though within the walls thereof, as the Parliament of England is to this City, which is ſo near adjoyning.</p>
            <p>If others doe object that our Generall hath not a Commiſſion from the Commons of England (for whoſe Liberties he and his Army now ſtands) to go againſt the Parliament, upon whatſoever colour or pretence? It is anſwered, that he and his Army have as faire a Commiſſion at leaſt, of the Commons ſo to doe, as <hi>Joab</hi> and his ſouldiers had of King <hi>David</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114327:10"/>or the Kingdome of Judah and Iſrael for what they did; but what out Army doth, is no wiſe againſt, but altogether for the Parliament in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as having relation to the well-being or better ſubſiſting thereof, chiefly by expulſion of corrupt and rotten Members, who have lately crept in, and over-voted the well-affected party in the Houſe, like ſo many drons in a hive: ſo that the Army onely leadeth their helping hand to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England in this caſe, for purging their Houſe of Commons, as they moſt powerfully and valiantly aſſiſted both them and the Parliament formerly in another caſe, by ſubduing all their open enemies, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them could do, even by all their former Armies.</p>
            <p>And if any would have further ſatisfaction herein, if they will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the 19. and 20. Chapters of the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> concerning <hi>Joabs</hi> Commiſſion in that his ſo faithfull ſervice to the King and Kingdome, with our Armies Ingagements, Declarations, Petitions, and Remonſtrances, concerning Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi>'s Commiſſion, in his ſo faithfull ſervice to the Kingdome of England, now in this our extreame neceſſitie, they will find that hee hath a better Commiſſion then <hi>Joab</hi> had in this his purſuit: for as the one proſecuted with zeale for the weale, ſafety, and recovery of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Liberties againſt all adverſaries, he onely knowing the mind of the better party, ſo with the like zeale doth our valiant Captaine proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute for the weal, ſafety and recovery of this Kingdomes Liberties, againſt all adverſarie powers, knowing the mind of the well affected, and at the earneſt requeſts and fervent deſires of many diſtreſſed and oppreſſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners, Priſoners, Widdowes, Fatherleſſe, maimed Souldiers, poore and others.</p>
            <p>And whereas it may be alledged, that our Generall is out of his office, and the Army ordered to be disbanded by the Parliament, who both gave him his office, &amp; them their power, for the uſe they were at firſt appointed? It is anſwered, what the Parliament gave either him or them, or took from him and them, they neither gave the one nor tooke the other, as they are an entire Corporation or State by themſelves alone, but as the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Body of all the Commons of England, and ſo in that reſpect, but their agents and ſervants, even as ſome Biſhop or Miniſter (after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet) doth annoint a King, being ſo ordained by the Kingdome, yet it doth not follow by any good conſequence, that ſuch a man meerly for his ſo officiating or diſcharging the duty of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, is King, Lord, or Maſter of ſuch a King ſo annointed by him, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill a ſubject or ſervant to him, becauſe he is ſo ordained by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as by a greater power then his owne, to performe that point of duty, as well as the reſt belonging to his Office.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:10"/>
            <p>And upon this conſideration, he may neither juſtly ſay, nor in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect dare avow, as <hi>Cardinall Weolſey</hi> preſumptuouſly wrote to the Pope, I and my King doe ſuch and ſuch things, ſo that both the Armie and the Parliament, or the Parliament and the Army, (which of them ſoever may juſtly at this time have the firſt place, as the caſe now ſtands, the one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the bare word, and the other the ſharp ſword) yea and the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though he were ſet as high as <hi>Solomon</hi> on his throne, are all but the Commons of Englands Servants, and they onely ordained for the weale and better being, but never for the woe and worſe being of the Common-wealth: whereas the Common-wealth was never ordained, for the better nor worſe being of them in any regard, but as they are ſervants to it, or as ſhepheards and watch-men in keeping it in peace, order, and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, both from forraigne and inteſtine enemies, and the other as ſpeciall inſtruments both of defending them in the diſcharge of their offices, and for that end, of maintaining them in their authorities.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Needfull Queres to the Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honourable and truly noble, at leaſt ſhould be, like the men of Berea,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOt to ſpeak of the crying ſins and great abominations, whereof the Kings, Parliaments, Prieſts and People of this Nation are guilty, even ſurpaſſing the ſinnes of Sodome and Gomorah, Tyrus and Sydon, in ſo long injoying, and yet never receiving nor obeying the glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt, which if they had had, as our Saviour ſaid of Capernaum and Bethſaidah, might poſſibly have brought forth better fruits then ever England did; neither to inſiſt of the innocent blood, which cryeth from heaven againſt this Nation, by our betraying, under the colour of helping, that worthy and ſtrong City Rochell, as well by cheating them of their proviſion in their extreame famine, when they were ſo ſtraightly beſieged, as by advancing their enemies with eight great ſhips to their utter ruine, ſtarving and deſolation, nor yet of the oceans of the guiltleſſe blood ſpilt, and treaſures ſpent, of late daies amongſt our ſelves, to ſmall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, yea and much thereof by your corruption, careleſſeneſſe, double-dealing, and other indirect and counterfeit meanes.</p>
            <p>Did ever any Nation give better aſſiſtance to any Parliament, then this diſtreſſed Nation have everie manner of way given unto you? Was it all done to make you Lords and Knights, and our ſelves but ſervants and ſlaves? Was it to ſet you all in Coaches, and on horſe-backe, and our
<pb facs="tcp:114327:11"/>ſelves but to run at your feet? Was it not meerely that ye ſhould redreſſe our grievances, and recover our Liberties, aboliſh wicked Lawes and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh good Lawes? But have ye performed to us either one or other of theſe your duties? Have ye not rather made the cure more grievous then the diſeaſe, and the laſt errour worſe then the firſt?</p>
            <p>Have ye ſo often proteſted, vowed, ſworne, and declared before God and the world, that you would deliver us from all oppreſſion and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie? and yet are not ye your ſelves become greater oppreſſors and tyrants then ever we had? Have ye not againſt all Law, juſtice, reaſon, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and profeſſion, both done many things ye ought not, and left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of things undone, which according to the ſame grounds, ye were bound to doe? Did either Petitions, Informations, or Admonitions ever prevaile with you by word or writing, but rather did you not hearden your hearts, more and more like <hi>Pharoah?</hi> Have ye not alwaies ſought rather to be revenged on ſuch as ſhew you your hainous ſinnes, then any wiſe (except in hypocriticall Faſts) to amend your faults? Yea, and I appeaſe to your owne conſciences, Are not all theſe but meere ſhewes which now ye make, to rectifie ſome of the innumerable things that are amiſſe by your owne meanes, even rather for ſlaviſh and guilty feare of the Armies ſword; then out of any dutifull reſpect or true favour to the Commons of England, who chooſed and truſted you, and whom (as yee are bound) ye ſhould both ſerve and reſpect, if ye made any conſcience of Gods VVord?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A faithfull Advice to the Armie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Renowned Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MAny of you know better then I can expreſſe, what wiſe courſe <hi>Joſuah</hi> that valiant Captaine Generall (who for a long time fought the Lord of Hoſtes Battells in the behalfe of his peculiar people the Jewes) did take when he ſaw the Lord ſhew himſelfe ſo angry at the ſins of the people, (though it was but of one man) that he made them both fall and fly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their enemies, he ſearcheth diligently (either by lot or otherwiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtome of thoſe days) throughout all the twelve Tribes, in which Tribe, or perſon of the Tribe the fault was; and finding it in the royall Tribe of Judah, and in <hi>Achan</hi> by name, through his covetouſneſſe, (which is the root of all evill) did puniſh him according to the nature of his fault.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114327:11"/>
            <p>Ye have both begun and run very well hetherto, yea and win one part of the prize, praiſed be God, but I pray, who lets you, that yee will not obey the truth, but ſeem to be weary of wel-doing: verily I ſay unto you, if ye ſit down to eat, drink, take tobacco, and riſe up to play, there will come ſuch another alarme and unexpected judgment to waken you, as now yee ſeem to be to the Parliament, that may both poſſibly and ſpeedily ſweep you all away. Remember that the fooliſh Virgins who knocked at heavens gates out of time were debarred.</p>
            <p>Ye know well enough (having ſuch principles) how dangerous it is, to begin in the Spirit and end in the fleſh; and that the more gifts ye have, the more inexcuſable ye are, if your practices be not anſwerable; have ye both done and ſuffered ſo many things in vaine, if ſo be it be even in vaine? All that ye can either do or ſuffer yet further, ſhall profit you nothing, if ye ſuffer your ſelves to be corrupted, bribed, penſioned divided, or delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. I wiſh they were even quite removed far from you, who trouble or diſquiet you by doubts, ſurmiſes, ſhifts, or delayes; yea and are not as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready to act and proſecute, as ye (in your grave reſolutions) are to conſult, debate and proceed.</p>
            <p>Ye both ſee and hear, yea and (I trow) yet feel, that there is not only one fault, and one party guiltie in the Parliament, where ye have begun to ſearch (though not yet with a candle, nor with a ſmall ſeive, but many, whereof ye accuſe ſome: well, if ye be they who ſhall deliver England, we need not look for others, proceed, &amp; go forth with courage like <hi>David,</hi> with your ſling-ſtones in your hands, in the name of the Lord of Hoſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all uncircumciſed Philiſtims, and quit your ſelves like men as ye have valiantly heretofore done, as your enemies cannot deny, for there is not only covetouſeſſe amongſt them, but both ambition and ſuperſtition in the higheſt degree, beſides horrible perjurie, adulterie, and all ſorts of iniquitie, yea or ſcarce one, who is not blemiſhed with that deceitfull Covenant, which all of them have both often and fearefully broken, and yet are ſo impudent and Sathanically wicked, that ſtill they urge and tempt others to come in the ſame dangerous ſnares with themſelves.</p>
            <p>If ye be diſcreet, and ſeeke the Kingdomes good more then your own, ye will not (like ſtanding water) lie ſtill and ſtink, and rot, and bring forth venomous beaſts, but ſhew your ſelves like cleare rivers which run into the Ocean, and both carry veſſells for the traffique of the Nations, and bring forth wholeſome and profitable fiſhes for mans uſe: Call to mind both how generous and valourous <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his ſouldiers were, who built the Temple with the one hand, and fought againſt the enemies with the other, and <hi>Abraham</hi> alſo who would not take a ſhooe-latchet in his
<pb facs="tcp:114327:12"/>victories againſt his enemies, but onely food to the ſouldiers, and if yee will ſpeedily performe now withall your power, whatſoever good your hands ſhall finde more to doe, (becauſe there is neither wiſdome, nor worke, nor invention in the grave whether ye go) and not put your hand to the plow, and (like <hi>Lots</hi> wife, or Iſrael in the wilderneſſe) look back, but forget what is behinde, and ſtrive forwards towards the marke, doubtleſſe the ſame God, who hath heretofore got himſelfe honour by you, will alſo upon your conſtant integrity and fidelity, in the diſcharge of your duty, ſtir up all other needfull inſtruments to aſſiſt you, untill he crowne his owne worke with perfection, and bring both his, your, and our unrecoverable enemies to deſtruction.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A Premonition to all Commons and Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, fore-warning them, that if they will ſet God before their eyes in all their practiſes, bee as true henceforth as they have been heretofore, to their owne native Countrey and Priviledges, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed valiantly as they have begun, he will ſo aſsiſt them, in crowning all their labours and toiles with victory, as glory may redound to him, and comfort to them and us, with all the poſterity.</head>
            <p>WHat meanes and craft can Sathan or his inſtruments deviſe, which guilty men will not uſe, to ſave themſelves from tryall, when both their own conſcience doe once begin to accuſe them and when a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full party bringeth a ſtrong accuſation againſt them? Will not all they who are in one fault be ſo far from confeſſing, that the will not only ſtick together (like abuſh of thornes or briers) but juſtifie and clear one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even to their utmoſt power, perſwading themſelves, that if a few of them ſhalbe brought to light, the reſt cannot long eſcape in darkneſſe?</p>
            <p>Therefore, to repent their evills, and prevent their tryalls, yea and dazle the peoples eyes, they doe not onely (ſince they began to be queſtioned) make great ſhewes of humiliation like <hi>Ahab,</hi> of zeale, like <hi>Jehu,</hi> and of obedience, like <hi>Saul,</hi> but likewiſe ſend forth their wiſe men, Councellors
<pb facs="tcp:114327:12"/>and Agents, (even Frogs, Machivillians, and Polititians) either to divide, delude, or diſperſe their accuſers, like Captain <hi>Drake</hi>'s ſhip in the midſt of the Spaniſh Fleet.</p>
            <p>And though they faile of their expectation herein, yet they ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage themſelves, (as <hi>Saul</hi> did, apprehending his owne guiltineſſe, he deſired nevertheleſſe to be honoured among the people,) and with great boldneſſe and impudencie, ſo face out the matter, that although by their ſecret means, ſome of their accuſers fellowes have alreadie loſt their lives, and will doe ſo with all the reſt, ſo ſoon as they can ſecretly (under other notions) provide an Army, yet they are not aſhamed now to owne their accuſers, and provide their wages, as being fleſh of their fleſh, and bone of their bones, yea and offer them all their deſires, onely juſtice, the eleven Members priſoners, and account of the Kingdomes moneyes, they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour yet to reſerve, till they ſee who will go up with them to Ramath Gilead, and proſper againſt the Army.</p>
            <p>But we hope the ſame God who hath freed us from regall oppreſſion, will alſo free us from Parliamentary corruption; and whether he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that this Army ſhould do it, or if we ſhould look for another, he knoweth beſt, who hath all the creatures at his call, to preſerve or puniſh whom he will; only thus much, if this Army do not ſet God before their eyes, and have no better principles, then for a poore meſſe of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies poyſoned pottage, to ſell both all their own birthrights and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and all the Commons of Englands liberties, for which they have ſo valiantly and victoriouſly ventured their lives, and will not perſevere in well-doing, without favour or feare, eſpecially having all the true-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Commons to partake with them, and aſſiſt them, and not crown their former victories, by ſparing either fat or leane, who are guilty and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; he who is onely wiſe and Almighty, knoweth very well both how to deale with them, and preſerve all that truſt in him.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
